Finding Aid for Metropolitan Christian Council (Detroit-Windsor) Records, 1920-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Metropolitan Christian Council (Detroit-Windsor) Records 1920-2006
Metropolitan Christian Council (Detroit-Windsor)
0637 Ba 2
The Metropolitan Christian Council (Detroit-Windsor) has been organizing the Detroit community around issues of faith since 1919. The record group documents the activities of the Council from the early 1920s until 2003. Records include annual reports produced by the Council, minutes from administrative meetings, pamphlets and promotional materials, photographs of council leadership and churches, topical files, and videotapes of television programs produced by the council.
8 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the Metropolitan Christian Council (Donor No. 8565 ), March 28, 2006.
The record group is open to research.
Prior to the formal establishment of the Metropolitan Detroit Council of Churches in 1919, cooperation among the area churches was limited to a Cooperative Council which acted (in the words of Council historian G. Merrill Lenox) as a "Comity Committee." Only a few of Detroit's churches were represented in this Council. At a meeting of the Cooperative Council in November 1918, the Rev. H. C. Gleiss reported for a Committee on Federation of the need to form "a comprehensive and aggressive federation of churches." The Council voted a Committee on Federation be formed, and that once the Federation was formed, the Cooperative Council would turn over its work to that new organization. On May 1, 1919, representatives of nine communions met and voted to establish the Detroit Council of Churches of Christ. At a subsequent meeting, Dr. Joseph A. Vance was elected to serve as president.
Throughout its history, the Council has adhered to the philosophy of "serving as a channel through which the churches can carry out unitedly all those functions which can best be performed through cooperative action." On matters of evangelism and social service and publicity, the Council was an invaluable tool for Detroit's local churches in providing broadly-based services. With its assistance, local churches were able to publicize their programs and special activities, and through its directory of churches and ministers, the Council established the framework for a network of local churches working together on common causes. The Council also took seriously its role in outlining the position the churches on issues of local, as well as state and national concern. The Council gave common voice to its church members on matters such as gambling, prohibition, McCarthyism, civil rights and the needs of the inner city, and other issues of morality.
The first office space occupied by the Council was in the Downtown Y.M.C.A. Thereafter it was headquartered in the rented offices in the Charlevoix Building, and then two locations in the Park Avenue Buildings. Sometime later it moved into its own quarters at 65 Columbia East, and thereafter into smaller rented offices.
In 1962, the word Metropolitan was added to the name to indicate the Council's service to the tri-county region of Wayne, Oakland, and Macomb Counties. In 1976, to better define its nature and to indicate its local autonomy, the name of the Council was again changed to Christian Communication Council of Metropolitan Detroit Churches. At that time services were expanded to reach 2000 congregations in eight counties: Essex (Ontario), Livingston, Macomb, Monroe, Oakland, Saint Clair, Washtenaw, and Wayne. Several communions were added to the mailing list, including Church of God in Christ, Missouri Lutheran, 10 Orthodox Christian denominations, Roman Catholic, Southern Baptist, 10 Canadian denominations, and others. The name was changed to Metropolitan Christian Council (Detroit - Windsor) in 2000 to more clearly indicate its international dimension.
Additional information about the Metropolitan Christian Council will be found in the commemorative history (to 1969) written by G. Merrill Lenox (located in the Topical File series under "History") and on the website: http://users.aol.com/councilweb/
The records of the Metropolitan Christian Council have been divided between two archival repositories. The first accession was given to the Walter Reuther Library, Wayne State University, in Detroit. A summary listing of these materials will be found in the Related Materials portion of this finding aid. In 2006, the Council, upon concurrence with archivists at the Reuther Library, donated additional records to the Bentley Historical Library. This second accession of records dates close to the founding of the organization and extends up to 2004. The series within the two accessions, however, do not seem to overlap and consist of different kinds of records.
The record group donated to the Bentley Library now comprises seven record series: Board of Directors, Council Packets, Programs, brochures, and other publications, Annual Reports, Topical Files, Television Programs, and General Assembly. In addition, the Council donated issues of its annual church directory and its newspaper -- The Newscaster-- which have been pulled from the records and cataloged separately.
Subjects:
Metropolitan Christian Council (Detroit-Windsor); Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Detroit (Mich.)--Religion.; Detroit Metropolitan Area (Mich.)--Religion.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Metropolitan Christian Council (Detroit-Windsor); Detroit Metropolitan Area (Mich.)--Religion.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Board of Directors Meeting Files
  The Board of Directors series includes minutes from the Board's meetings between 1943 and 2002. These meetings determined the council's activities and dealt with budget issues as well.
  - 1943-1945 (Box 1)
  - 1946-1948 (Box 1)
  - 1949-1954 (Box 1)
  - 1955-1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958-1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1963 (Box 1)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - 1992-1993 (Box 2)
  - 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - 1996-1997 (Box 2)
  - 1998-1999 (Box 2)
  - 2000-2002 (Box 2)
- Council Packets
  The Council Packets series consists of information sent out by the Council to constituent ministries from 1976 to 2000. Four packets were sent out each year and were intended to update ministries on the council's activities and initiatives.
  - 1976 (Box 2)
  - 1977 (Box 2)
  - 1978 (Box 2)
  - 1979 (Box 2)
  - 1980 (Box 2)
  - 1981 (Box 2)
  - 1982 (Box 2)
  - 1984 (Box 3)
  - 1985 (Box 3)
  - 1986 (Box 3)
  - 1987 (Box 3)
  - 1989 (Box 3)
  - 1990 (Box 3)
  - 1991 (Box 3)
  - 1992 (Box 3)
  - 1993 (Box 3)
  - 1994 (Box 3)
  - 1995 (Box 3)
  - 1996 (Box 3)
  - 1997 (Box 4)
  - 1998 (Box 4)
  - 1999 (Box 4)
  - 2000 (Box 4)
- Programs, brochures, and other publications
  The Programs, brochures, and other publications series contains promotional and informational materials created by the Council and programs and related materials from special services.
  - Ash Wednesday service 1973-1999 (Box 4)
    (some gaps)
  - Christmas Carol Festival 1947-1967 (Box 4)
  - Detroit Pastor's Union / Michigan Pastors' Conference 1951-1958 (Box 4)
  - Lent and Good Friday Services 1940s-1960s (Box 4)
  - Promotional brochures and tracts, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Protestant Reformation Festival Materials 1947-1966 (Box 4)
  - Michigan State Fair Sunrise Services 1947-1973 (Box 4)
    (include photographs)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Annual Reports
  The Annual Reports series contains the annual reports produced by the council and reports produced by the social workers working for the council.
  - Annual Meeting Program and Reports 1920-1967 (Box 4)
  - Annual Reports of Council Departments (Box 5)
    - 1947-1957 (Box 5)
    - 1958-1968 (Box 5)
  - Annual Reports of Social Service Workers 1922-1942 (Box 5)
- Topical Files
  Topical Files document the varied activities and initiatives of the council, ranging from awards given to photos to information on gambling and child abuse.
  - 75th Anniversary 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - Audit 1989-2003 (Box 5)
  - Birmingham School for Special Children 1962-1971 (Box 5)
  - "Black Manifesto" 1969 (Box 5)
  - Board Attendance 1990-1996 (Box 5)
  - Business Unit Minutes 1987-1998 (Box 5)
  - Casino Gambling 1987 (Box 5)
  - Child Abuse circa 1976 (Box 5)
  - Communication Activities 1971 (Box 5)
  - Consultation on Church Union (COCU) (Box 5)
  - Critical Letters 1970-1972 (Box 5)
  - Cults 1979 (Box 5)
  - Church Merit Awards 1977-1991 (Box 5)
  - Daedal Doors (Box 5)
  - Directory Contract 2006 (Box 5)
  - Funding 1997-1998 (Box 5)
  - Greater Detroit Study Commission. Report entitled "Toward a Center for Theological Studies" July 1964 (Box 5)
  - History by G, Merrill Lenox entitled "Christian Unity & Mission" 1969 (Box 6)
  - Institute on Judaism, Rabbi B. Benedict & Ada S. Glazer 1979-2005 (Box 6)
  - Inter-Faith Action Council 1969 (Box 6)
  - Inter-religious Foundation for Community Organization 1969 (Box 6)
  - Kerr Ecumenical Award 1992-1998 (Box 6)
  - Layman of the Year 1954-1968 (Box 6)
  - Lenten Materials (Box 6)
  - Media (Box 6)
  - Meals for Shut-ins Christmas Songs (Box 6)
  - Muslim-Christian-Jewish leadership forum (Box 6)
  - Newscaster (Box 6)
  - Pastor's Association (Box 6)
  - Photographs and related information
    - Baumgartner, Robert R. (Box 6)
    - Bright, J. Russell (Box 6)
    - Brumbaugh, Thoburn T. (Box 6)
    - Emrich, Bishop Richard S. (Box 6)
    - Johnstone, R. T. (Box 6)
    - Lenox, G. Merrill (Box 6)
    - Lindsay, Kenneth (Box 6)
    - Littler, Mark D. (Box 6)
    - Roberts, Joseph L. (Box 6)
    - Zaun, Allan A. (Box 6)
    - Council Building photos (Box 6)
    - Kirk-in-the-Hills (Box 6)
  - Planning Unit for Theological Concerns (Box 6)
  - Proposal for a Council of Black Churchmen 1969-1971 (Box 6)
  - Restructuring, proposed circa 1972-1976, 1 volumes (Box 6)
    (include New Ecumenical Communication / Service Organization, study document and other materials)
  - Willingham, Edward B. (Box 6)
- Television Programs 1992-2004, U-matic videotapes
  Television Programs were filmed by Bloomfield Community Television and include artistic performances and discussions of faith-based issues. These twelve U-matic videotape cassettes are a small sample of the Council's two weekly television series "Interfaith Odyssey" round table discussions and "Daedal Doors" for children.
  - Interfaith Odyssey 2001-2004
    - The Uninsured and the Underinsured April 2004 (Box 7)
    - Daily Prayer March 2004 (Box 7)
    - Healing July 2002 (Box 7)
    - Has There Been a Change in the American People Since 9/11? August 2003 (Box 7)
    - The Use of Violence to Obtain Justice-What Does Your Religion Say About This? October 2001 (Box 7)
    - How Far Does Your Religion Go in Support of the President? October 2001 (Box 7)
    - Equality of Men & Women May 2003 (Box 7)
    - An In-depth Look at the Muslim Community September 2003 (Box 7)
  - Daedal Doors
    - Astronauts October 1995 (Box 7)
    - Youth Drama is Exciting. Part II: The Agape Dancers & Bethel A.M.E. Church Drama Club February 2002 (Box 7)
    - What's Your Dream? March 1992 (Box 7)
    - And the Beat Goes On/Highland Park Steppers February 1999 (Box 7)
- General Assembly
  The General Assembly files date from 1976 to 1996 and include such materials as programs, agendas, brochures, and various mailings and reports.
  - 1976-October 1996, 42 folders (Box 8)
Related Material at the Walter Reuther Library
The Archives of Labor and Urban Affairs of the Walter P. Reuther Library, Wayne State University holds a significant portion of the Council’s records. The records have been cataloged as the Metropolitan Detroit Council of Churches Collection. The following is a brief summarization of this collection. It has been arranged into two parts or accessions.
Part I Series:
National Council of Churches, 1955-1963, box 1.
Michigan Council of Churches general business and education departments, 1957-1963, box 2.
Metropolitan Detroit Council of Churches general office and agency files, 1956-1965, boxes 3-4.
Religious Education, 1922-1964, boxes 4-7.
Public Affairs Department general office files, 1950-1967, boxes 8-10.
Peace and International Relations, 1964-1966.
General subject file, 1950-1967, boxes 12-14.
Division of family life, 1947-1969, boxes 12-14.
Detroit Council of Religious Education Division of Christian Education, 1950-1960, boxes 14-17.
Miscellaneous, 1929-1969, box 17.
The Church Newscaster, 1956-1971, boxes 17-18
Part II Series:
MDCC Reports of annual meetings and financial reports, 1932-1964, boxes 1-2.
Executive Secretary subject files, 1939-1967, boxes 2-5.
Social Services Department, 1920-1964, boxes 5-7.
Council affiliated organizations and annual events, 1947-1968, boxes 7-9.
Public Affairs Department, 1959-1967, boxes 9-10.
Department of Church Extension, 1953-1966, boxes 10-12.
Department of Evangelism, 1931-1933, 1950-59, box 12.